Register of the Juraj Slávik Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Juraj Slávik papers,
1918-1968
76087
Slávik, Juraj, 1890-
54 manuscript boxes, 5 envelopes, 3 microfilm reels (23.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, dispatches, memoranda, telegrams, clippings, and photographs, relating to Czechoslovak relations with Poland and the United States, political developments in Czechoslovakia, Czechoslovak emigration and émigrés, and anti-Communist movements in the United States.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (51 reels).
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1890 January 28 Born in Dobrá Niva, Slovakia
1910-1911 Ecole de Droit, Paris
1911 College de France, Paris
1913 Received his law degree from the University of Budapest
1918 Secretary of the Slovak National Council, Bratislava
1926 Minister of Agriculture and of the Unification of Laws (appointed by Jan Masaryk)
1929-1932 Minister of the Interior
1929-1935 Member of Parliament
1936 February 1 - 1939 March 15 Ambassador to Poland
1939 summer Went on lecture tour in the United States for three months (started liberation movement along with Beneš)
1939 July Went back to Poland to help Czechoslovak soldiers, officers, and airmen escape from Hitler-occupied Czechoslovakia
1939 September Left for France after the war started
1939-1940 Member of the Czechoslovak National Committee in Paris
1940 June Left Paris for London
1940-1945 Minister of the Interior and Minister of Education, Government-in-Exile, London Broadcast via BBC to Hitler-occupied Czechoslovakia
1945 May Returned to Czechoslovakia
1945 June - 1946 June Worked at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
1946 June - 1948 March Ambassador to the United States
1946-1947 Accompanied Jan Masaryk to the Paris Peace Conference Member of the Czechoslovak Delegation to the United Nations
1948 March 3 Resigned his post as ambassador in protest against the coup d'état in Czechoslovakia ("I have decided to fight for Czechoslovak democracy")
1949 Member of the Executive Board and Chairman of the Social-Aid Committee of the Council of Free Czechoslovakia
1954? Chairman of the Cultural Committee of the Assembly of Captive European Nations
1969 May Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Juraj Slávik papers were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives from his wife, Gita Slávik, in two installments. The first, which arrived in May 1976, included material relating to Slávik's government service in Poland and the United States, Czechoslovak emigration and emigres, and anti-communist movements in the U.S. The second installment arrived in July 1978 and consisted of correspondence, personal documents, photographs, and microfilm relating to Slávik's service as a statesman, and his memoirs.
The bulk of the collection consists of Slávik's speeches and writings, namely his numerous lectures in Great Britain during World War II, his patriotic radio speeches broadcast to Czechoslovakia by the BBC for the London-based Czechoslovak government-in-exile during World War II, as well as his writings on the history of Slovakia and its role within Czechoslovakia (see, in the speeches and writings file, "Slovakia within the Czechoslovak Republic," "Slovensko až do dneška," and "Protectorate Slovakia").
Of great importance are Slávik's memoirs entitled "Moja pamať - živá kniha (My Memory - A Living Book), which were published as a series of articles in New Yorkský Denník during the years 1955-1957. They explain the events that contributed to the downfall of Czechoslovakia and Poland in 1938 and 1939, describe the beginning of the Czechoslovak exile movement in 1939 and 1940, the creation and activities of the Czechoslovak National Committee in Paris, and the deeds and fate of the Czechoslovak provisional government in London in 1940-1945.
Of special note in the career file are Slávik's numerous dispatches and reports from the Czechoslovak Legation in Warsaw to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Prague, shedding some light on Czechoslovakia's relations with Poland before World War II. Also interesting in that series are materials relating to the peace settlement at the end of World War II and population transfers (see Ambassador to the United States in the career file).
Of great importance are also documents on Czechoslovak emigration and emigres, and anti-communist movements in the U.S. (see Member, Council of Free Czechoslovakia in the career file).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; Czechs in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Poland.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--United States.; Czechoslovakia--History--1938-1945.; Czechoslovakia--History--Coup d'état, 1948.; Czechoslovakia--Politics and government.; Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo zahranicnich veci.
Occupations
Statesmen--Czechoslovakia.; Diplomats--Czechoslovakia.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1919-1968. (Box 1-2)
  Biographical information, certificates, correspondence, financial papers, lists, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Applications (Folder 1: 1)
  - Articles and clippings about Slávik (Folder 1: 2)
  - Awards (Folder 1: 3)
  - Biographical sketches (Folder 1: 4)
  - Certificates (Folder 1: 5)
  - Citizenship papers (Folder 1: 6)
  - Diary (Folder 1: 7)
  - Family correspondence (Folder 1: 8-9)
  - Financial records. (Folder 1: 10)
    Includes some correspondence
  - Identity papers. (Folder 1: 11)
    Includes membership cards and passes
  - Information sent to Slávik from various individuals about the political and economic situation in Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Poland, Romania, Slovakia, covering the period 1940-1955 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
  - Invitations (Folder 2: 4)
  - Reports received by Slávik from Warsaw from editor Hejret? after his departure in March 1939 (Folder 2: 5-7)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 2: 8)
- Correspondence, 1918-1968. (Box 3-12)
  Letters, notes, and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - A (Folder 3: 1)
    - B (Folder 3: 2)
    - C (Folder 3: 3)
    - D (Folder 3: 4)
    - E (Folder 3: 5)
    - F (Folder 3: 6)
    - G (Folder 3: 7)
    - H (Folder 3: 8)
    - I (Folder 3: 9)
    - J (Folder 3: 10)
    - K (Folder 3: 11)
    - L (Folder 3: 12)
    - M (Folder 3: 13)
    - N (Folder 3: 14)
    - O (Folder 3: 15)
    - P (Folder 3: 16)
    - R (Folder 3: 17)
    - S (Folder 3: 18)
    - T (Folder 3: 19)
    - U (Folder 3: 20)
    - V-W (Folder 3: 21)
    - Z (Folder 3: 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 3: 23)
  - Unidentified, 1938-1968 (Folder 3: 24-25)
  - A. Powell Davies Memorial Committee, 1958 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Adams, Paul Louison, 1948 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Albright, Charles A., 1950 (Folder 4: 3)
  - All Souls' Church Unitarian, 1949-1957 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Ambrož, Anton P., 1955-1956 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Ambulance Trust Fund, 1940 (Folder 4: 6)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1948 (Folder 4: 7)
  - American Czechoslovak Centre, Inc., 1957 (Folder 4: 8)
  - American Friends of Czechoslovakia, 1946 (Folder 4: 9)
  - American Fund for Czechoslovak Refugees, Inc., 1948-1963., See also Career file/Member, Council of Free Czechoslovakia (Folder 4: 10)
  - American Liberation Committee for Spiš and Orava, Chicago, 1951 (Folder 4: 11)
  - The American Mercury, 1949 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Anderle, Josef, 1964-1965 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Andic, V. E., 1949-1962 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Andráš, Julius, 1957 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Andrial, Jindřich, 1948 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Anglo-Czechoslovak Christian Fellowship, 1943 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Antl, Fred, 1939 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Antošík, Jozef, 1948-1950 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Ashton, 1944 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Augustine Herman Czech American Historical Society, 1954-1963 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Balint, Nicholas, 1954-1957 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Barbaric, M., 1948 (Folder 4: 23)
  - Barnes & Nobles, Inc., 1965 (Folder 4: 24)
  - Baťa, Tomas, 1939 (Folder 4: 25)
  - Bedo, Alexander, 1955-1956 (Folder 4: 26)
  - Behárka, Jan, 1950 (Folder 4: 27)
  - Bělohlávek, n.d. (Folder 4: 28)
  - Benedict, J., 1939 (Folder 4: 29)
  - Beneš, Edvard, 1940-1942., See also Career file/Ambassador to the United States (Folder 4: 30)
  - Bervida, Jan, n.d. (Folder 4: 31)
  - Biddle, Anthony, 1939-1941 (Folder 4: 32)
  - Biddle, Margaret, n.d. (Folder 4: 33)
  - Bielecki, T., 1955 (Folder 4: 34)
  - Biggs, n.d. (Folder 4: 35)
  - Bloch, Josef, 1940 (Folder 4: 36)
  - Bogomolov, Alexander J., 1941 (Folder 4: 37)
  - Boháč, Vladimír, 1946 (Folder 4: 38)
  - Boitin-Jasinská, Myra, 1948 (Folder 4: 39)
  - Bothwell, James H., 1955-1956 (Folder 4: 40)
  - Bratislava (Czechoslovakia). Primátor hlavního města Bratislavy (Mayor of the city of Bratislava), 1947 (Folder 4: 41)
  - British Council, 1941-1944 (Folder 4: 42)
  - Brož, J., 1941 (Folder 4: 43)
  - Bujna, Ivan, 1951-1964 (Folder 4: 44)
  - Burckhardt, Carl J., 1966 (Folder 4: 45)
  - Bureš, Jaroslav, 1953 (Folder 4: 46)
  - Canada. Legation (Czechoslovakia), 1947 (Folder 4: 47)
  - Čapek, J., 1940 (Folder 4: 48)
  - Carr, Edith K., 1948 (Folder 4: 49)
  - Catholic Department of Visual Education, 1947 (Folder 4: 50)
  - Čechoslovák, 1943 (Folder 4: 51)
  - The Central European Federalist, 1958 (Folder 4: 52)
  - Čermák, Josef, 1956 (Folder 4: 53)
  - Černý, František, 1953 (Folder 4: 54)
  - Černý, Vladimír, 1940 (Folder 5: 1)
  - České Národní Sdružení v Americe (Czech-American National Alliance), 1947 (Folder 5: 2)
  - České Slovo, 1963-1968 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Československá Filatelistická Společnost (The Czechoslovak Philatelic Society), 1944 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Československá Hospodářská Poradna (Czechoslovak Economic Advisory Association), 1940-1944 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Československá Informační Služba (Czechoslovak Information Service), 1946 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Československá Národní Rada v Americe (Czechoslovak National Council of America), 1939-1968 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Československá Zahraniční Akce, 1941 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Československé Národné Sdruženie v Kanade (Czechoslovak National Association of Canada), 1957-1959 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Československé Sdružení Politických Uprchlíků v Německu (Czechoslovak Alliance of Political Refugees in Germany), 1950 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Československé Ústředí (Czechoslovak Centre), 1941-1943 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Československý Červený Kříž (Czechoslovak Red Cross), 1942 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Československý Institut (Czechoslovak Institute), 1941-1944 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Československý Klub (Czechoslovak Club), 1954 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Československý Pomocný Výbor (Czechoslovak Relief Committee), 1948., See also Career file/Member, Council of Free Czechoslovakia (Folder 5: 15)
  - Československý Studijní Ústav (Czechoslovak Research Institute), 1943 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Chalupa, Josef, 1953 (Folder 5: 17)
  - The Chaplain School, 1946-1949 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Charles Carroll American Heritage Association, n.d. (Folder 5: 19)
  - Chomutovský, Jan, 1956 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Christ Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1958 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Clementis, Vladimír, 1946-1948., See also Career file/ Ambassador to the United States (Folder 5: 22)
  - Colonie Tchécoslovaque de France, 1943 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Cook, Thomas, 1942 (Folder 5: 24)
  - The Cooperative Forum, 1948 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Coste, Brutus, 1955 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Costello, D. P., n.d. (Folder 5: 27)
  - Crockett, J., 1960 (Folder 5: 28)
  - Cuba. Legation (Czechoslovakia), 1947 (Folder 5: 29)
  - Curtis, Tony, 1952 (Folder 5: 30)
  - Cvrk, Karol, 1953 (Folder 5: 31)
  - The Czech Refugee Trust Fund, 1941 (Folder 5: 32)
  - Czechoslovak British Society, 1942 (Folder 5: 33)
  - Czechoslovak Medical Association in Great Britain, 1941 (Folder 5: 34)
  - The Czechoslovak Presbytarian Church of Jan Hus, 1948 (Folder 5: 35)
  - The Czechoslovak Presbytarian Church of Sts. Cyril and Method, 1939 (Folder 5: 36)
  - Czechoslovak Press, Inc. (former CS Publishing Co., Inc.), 1955-1956 (Folder 5: 37)
  - Czechoslovakia. Místokonzulát (Birmingham), 1942 (Folder 5: 38)
  - Czechoslovakia. Velvyslanectví (United States), 1939-1946 (Folder 5: 39)
  - Daniel, Andrej, 1939 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Danish Council (London, England), 1945 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Davenport, Marcia, 1967-1968 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Davies, A. Powell, 1953 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Davies, Mrs., 1957 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Davis, Lionberger J., 1949-1950 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Demec, n.d., See also Biographical file/Information sent to Slávik from various individuals (Folder 6: 7)
  - Denní Hlasatel, 1955 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Dietz, William L., 1948 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Dohnálek, Jan, 1947 (Folder 6: 10)
  - Dominican Republic. Embajada (United States), 1946 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Doubková, Jarmila, 1948 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Ducháček, Ivo, 1940 (Folder 6: 13)
  - Dvořáková, Růžena, 1948 (Folder 6: 14)
  - Dvouletý, Ota, 1941-1945 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Edinger, George, 1942 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Eisner, 1948 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Eret, J., 1961 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Estes, Charles T., 1948 (Folder 6: 19)
  - The Europa Service, 1942 (Folder 6: 20)
  - F.C.I. News and Features from Behind the Iron Curtain, 1964 (Folder 6: 21)
  - Fabry, Milan, 1950 (Folder 6: 22)
  - Falta, Josef, 1955 (Folder 6: 23)
  - Faltusová, A., 1964 (Folder 6: 24)
  - Fanderlík, V., 1952 (Folder 6: 25)
  - Federated Slovak Societies, 1939 (Folder 6: 26)
  - Federation of Czechoslovak Jews, 1942 (Folder 6: 27)
  - Federation of Free Hungarian Jurists in America, 1955 (Folder 6: 28)
  - Feierabend, Ladislav, 1950 (Folder 6: 29)
  - Fierlinger, Zdeněk, 1939 (Folder 6: 30)
  - Firkušný, Rudolf, 1948 (Folder 6: 31)
  - First Foundation for Freedom, n.d. (Folder 6: 32)
  - Firt, J., 1950-1956 (Folder 6: 33)
  - Fischl, Viktor, 1941 (Folder 6: 34)
  - Florin, 1941-1946 (Folder 6: 35)
  - Foltz, John F., 1968 (Folder 6: 36)
  - Formánek, Z., 1954 (Folder 6: 37)
  - Fotitch, C., n.d. (Folder 6: 38)
  - La France libre, 1940-1941 (Folder 6: 39)
  - France. Ministère de la Guerre, 1940., See also Career file/Czechoslovak National Committee (Folder 6: 40)
  - France. Ministère des Affaires Etrangères, 1940., See also Career file/Member, Czechoslovak National Committee (Folder 6: 41)
  - Frank, 1948-1956 (Folder 6: 42)
  - Fried, Antonin, 1949 (Folder 6: 43)
  - Friedlander, Robert A., 1963 (Folder 6: 44)
  - The German Social Democratic Labour Party of the Czechoslovak Republic, 1941 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Gerstel, Emil, 1937 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Goldstucker, Eduard, 1942 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Goplen, Adne, 1961 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Great Britain. Embassy (United States), 1963 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Great Britain. Ministry of Information, 1941 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Great Britain. Parliament, 1943 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Grim, George, 1948 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Gromada, Thaddeus, 1952-1963 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Grossmann, H., 1942 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Haljan, Pavel, 1952 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Hanuš, K., 1940 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Havel, Miloš, 1953 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Heller, Francis H., 1939 (Folder 7: 14)
  - Herben, Ivan, 1948-1957 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Herzan, Josef, 1948 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Hlavatý, Václav, 1955-1956 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Hník, F. M., 1940-1944 (Folder 7: 18)
  - Hodžová, Glasa, 1947 (Folder 7: 19)
  - Hodžová, Irena, 1944 (Folder 7: 20)
  - Hofmann, Josef, 1947 (Folder 7: 21)
  - Holy Cross Lutheran Church, 1939 (Folder 7: 22)
  - Holy Trinity Slovak Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1956 (Folder 7: 23)
  - The Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion, 1943-1945 (Folder 7: 24)
  - Hovorka, 1949 (Folder 7: 25)
  - Howe, Mary Louise, n.d. (Folder 7: 26)
  - Hřebík, Antonín, 1957 (Folder 7: 27)
  - Hromádka, Professor, n.d. (Folder 7: 28)
  - Hugan, Mišo, 1940., See also Biographical file/ Information sent to Slávik from various individuals (Folder 7: 29)
  - Hůlka, J. H., 1939 (Folder 7: 30)
  - Hvasta, J., 1956 (Folder 7: 31)
  - Hynko, Ladislav, 1947-1950., See also Biographical file/ Information sent to Slávik from various individuals (Folder 7: 32)
  - India. Embassy (United States), 1948 (Folder 7: 33)
  - Indiana University, 1960 (Folder 7: 34)
  - Ingrová, Gita, 1956 (Folder 7: 35)
  - Institute of Public Affairs, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1939 (Folder 7: 36)
  - Inter-Allied Publications, 1950 (Folder 7: 37)
  - International P.E.N. Club, 1941-1964 (Folder 7: 38)
  - International Spanish Speaking Association of Physicians, Inc., 1948 (Folder 7: 39)
  - Jablonický, Josef, n.d. (Folder 7: 40)
  - Jamnický, Otokar, 1945 (Folder 7: 41)
  - Jan Hus Presbytarian Church, 1939 (Folder 7: 42)
  - Jandáček, Antonín, 1948 (Folder 7: 43)
  - Janečka, n.d. (Folder 7: 44)
  - Jenček, Přemysl, 1948 (Folder 7: 45)
  - Jenkowitz, Wladyslaw, 1929-1937 (Folder 7: 46)
  - Jíra, Jaroslav, 1948 (Folder 7: 47)
  - Jirák, Karel, 1948 (Folder 7: 48)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1964 (Folder 7: 49)
  - Josten, Josef, 1948 (Folder 7: 50)
  - Jurasz, Prof., 1941 (Folder 7: 51)
  - Jurčák, Emil, 1945 (Folder 7: 52)
  - Just, Emil, 1948 (Folder 7: 53)
  - Kalabza, Albert, 1954 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Kallik, Ferdinand, n.d. (Folder 8: 2)
  - Kantůrková, Slávka, 1954 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Keedick, Lee, 1948 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Kisel, Jan, 1947-1959 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Klecanda, Vladimír, 1944 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Klimek, Adolf, 1955 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Kočarik, S., 1950 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Kolaja, Jiří, 1964-1965 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Koloman, Derek, 1948-1955 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Koordinační Výbor Československo-Polský, 1941 (Folder 8: 11)
  - Korbel, Josef, 1942., See also Career file/Minister, Government-in-Exile and Speeches and writings/General/Transcripts of radio broadcasts/BBC (Folder 8: 12)
  - Korbel, Pavel, 1961 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Korbonski, Stefan, 1954 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Koreň, Ludo, 1937 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Koutník, Stanislav, 1957 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Kováč, Ondrej, 1950 (Folder 8: 17)
  - Kovacik, Jan, 1966-1968 (Folder 8: 18)
  - Kozáčková, Marie, 1946 (Folder 8: 19)
  - Kozák, Václav, 1948 (Folder 8: 20)
  - Král, A., 1940 (Folder 8: 21)
  - Krno, L. G., 1947 (Folder 8: 22)
  - Kruzliak, Imrich, 1963 (Folder 8: 23)
  - Kuran, Rudolf, 1947 (Folder 8: 24)
  - Kusý, G., 1948 (Folder 8: 25)
  - Kybal, Vlastimil, 1948 (Folder 8: 26)
  - Kyslický, Jan, 1964 (Folder 8: 27)
  - Lampel, Otto, 1961-1965 (Folder 8: 28)
  - Lásková, Maria, 1950-1965 (Folder 8: 29)
  - Laštovička, R., 1947 (Folder 8: 30)
  - Lehman, Herbert, 1946 (Folder 8: 31)
  - Lekavý, Petr, 1949 (Folder 8: 32)
  - Lennard, E. W., 1943 (Folder 8: 33)
  - Lesák, Emil, 1948 (Folder 8: 34)
  - Lettrich, Jozef, 1947-1955 (Folder 8: 35)
  - Lexa, John G., 1964 (Folder 8: 36)
  - Lichner, Patricio, 1957 (Folder 8: 37)
  - Linden, Juraj, 1957 (Folder 8: 38)
  - The Ling Physical Education Association, 1942 (Folder 8: 39)
  - Loutchan, Ludmila, 1948 (Folder 8: 40)
  - Lowrie, Donald A., 1963 (Folder 8: 41)
  - Ludo, 1938 (Folder 8: 42)
  - Luža, Radomír, 1960-1967 (Folder 8: 43)
  - Lysý, Alois, 1953 (Folder 8: 44)
  - Malík, Josef, 1940 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Masaryk, Jan, 1946 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Masaryk Memorial Hall, Inc., 1956 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Masaryk Society (Manchester), 1941 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Masaryková, Alice, 1955-1957 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1948 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Matašovský, Jozef, 1956 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Matlocha, Jan, 1939 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Matula, George, 1962 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Maudr, Vladimír A., 1947 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Mihalko, Anna H., 1948 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Mladé Československo, 1942 (Folder 9: 12)
  - Moravec, F., 1940 (Folder 9: 13)
  - Mosely, Philip E., 1948 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Múdrý, Michael, 1954-1957 (Folder 9: 15)
  - Národný Slovenský Spolok, 1939 (Folder 9: 16)
  - Naše Cesta, 1954 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Naše Hlasy, 1955-1964 (Folder 9: 18)
  - Naše Noviny, 1942 (Folder 9: 19)
  - Našim ve Francii, 1957 (Folder 9: 20)
  - National Alliance of Slovak Lutherans, 1939 (Folder 9: 21)
  - National Committee for a Free Europe, 1950-1965 (Folder 9: 22)
  - National Conference on Citizenship, 1965-1968 (Folder 9: 23)
  - National Geographic Society, 1956-1965 (Folder 9: 24)
  - National Slovak Society, n.d. (Folder 9: 25)
  - Navrátil, Jaroslav, 1918 (Folder 9: 26)
  - Nehasil, A. L., 1953-1960 (Folder 9: 27)
  - Nehněvajsa, Jiří, 1948 (Folder 9: 28)
  - Němec, František, 1947-1958 (Folder 9: 29)
  - New Democratic Hungary, n.d. (Folder 9: 30)
  - The New York Times, 1955 (Folder 9: 31)
  - New Yorské Listy, 1946-1964 (Folder 9: 32)
  - New Yorkský Denník, 1943-1955 (Folder 9: 33)
  - Nosco, B., 1955 (Folder 9: 34)
  - Nosko, Jan M., 1964 (Folder 9: 35)
  - Novák, Emil, n.d. (Folder 9: 36)
  - Novomeský, Laco, 1947 (Folder 9: 37)
  - Oberleitner, Wolfgang E., 1964 (Folder 9: 38)
  - Ogilby, Remsen B., 1939 (Folder 9: 39)
  - Okrucký, Edmund, 1955 (Folder 9: 40)
  - Opočenská, J. M., 1968 (Folder 9: 41)
  - Osuský, Štefan, n.d. (Folder 9: 42)
  - Outrata, Vladimír, n.d. (Folder 9: 43)
  - Palovič, Julius, 1937-1946 (Folder 9: 44)
  - Papánek, Jan, 1948-1954 (Folder 9: 45)
  - Papež, Oldřich, 1953 (Folder 9: 46)
  - Parke-Bernet Galleries, Inc., 1966 (Folder 9: 47)
  - Pauliny, Miss, n.d. (Folder 9: 48)
  - Páv, Antonín, 1945 (Folder 9: 49)
  - Pavlů, Feodora B. (Feďa), 1950-1955 (Folder 9: 50)
  - Pentz, John A., 1959 (Folder 9: 51)
  - People to People Program, 1957 (Folder 9: 52)
  - Peressenyi, Juraj, 1951 (Folder 9: 53)
  - Pluhař, Josef, n.d. (Folder 9: 54)
  - The Poetry Society (London), 1942 (Folder 9: 55)
  - Poland. Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji, 1941 (Folder 9: 56)
  - Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America (New York), 1965 (Folder 9: 57)
  - Polish National Alliance, Chicago, 1951 (Folder 9: 58)
  - Polish Press Agency, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Polish Research Centre (London), 1941 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Pospíšil, Leopold, 1953-1956 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Procházka, Adolf, 1948-1956 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Procházka, B. J., 1948 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Procházka, Theodor, 1956-1963 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Prosek, Vratislav, 1959 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Proškovi, 1939 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Provazníková, Marie, 1950-1964 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Radimský, Ladislav, 1950-1964 (Folder 10: 10)
  - Radio Free Europe, 1958 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Raichl, Pravomil, 1953 (Folder 10: 12)
  - Rašín, Miroslav, 1948 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Richter, Josef, 1948 (Folder 10: 14)
  - Riedl? 1950-1956 (Folder 10: 15)
  - Ripka, Hubert, 1941-1957 (Folder 10: 16)
  - Rotary International (United Nations Rotary Outpost in London), 1942-1944 (Folder 10: 17)
  - Royal Canadian Legion, 1964 (Folder 10: 18)
  - The Royal Empire Society, 1941 (Folder 10: 19)
  - Rychtera, Ludvík, 1956 (Folder 10: 20)
  - S. S. Cyrill and Methodius Rectory, 1960 (Folder 10: 21)